<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>bysputnikus</title><link>https://sputnikus.github.io/</link><description></description><atom:link href="https://sputnikus.github.io/feeds/main.xml" rel="self"></atom:link><lastBuildDate>Tue, 03 Jun 2014 00:00:00 +0200</lastBuildDate><item><title>Stoicism with Zen tools</title><link>https://sputnikus.github.io/stoic_zen</link><description>&lt;p&gt;After years of fascination by east philosophy, I&amp;#8217;ve found much more suiting way of thinking about life closer, namely in ancient Greece and Rome. Stoic texts have much more impact on me than anything from Zen authors. There&amp;#8217;s a lot of misunderstanding of what Stoicism really means and I&amp;#8217;m not going to describe it today (but it&amp;#8217;s most certainly on my &lt;em&gt;to write&lt;/em&gt; Trello board). Instead I try to describe, what I&amp;#8217;ve taken from Zen philosophy that&amp;#8217;s helping me in day to day&amp;nbsp;Stoicism.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="meditation"&gt;Meditation&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Rise and shine. Yes, Iusually meditate on the morning (right after finishing a huge soup mug of bulletproof coffee). Now, there are some Stoic ways to meditate, like &lt;a href="http://newstoa.com/books/02_WILL%20POWER.pdf"&gt;Pneuma&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;a href="http://stoicscollege.com/books/08_SAM_II.pdf"&gt;Stick Action Meditation&lt;/a&gt;. But for me, mindfull Zen meditation is much more beneficial. It improves my sleep, makes my brain declutter and sort of restart. So every morning I try to sit down and focus on my breathing, for at least 5 minutes (any longer for&amp;nbsp;bonus).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="mindfulness"&gt;Mindfulness&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Both Zen and Stoicism are about stripping down of the sense of self. Yet the differs when it comes to how to put up with full presence in the moment. While Zen is more about acceptance what&amp;#8217;s happening, Stoics try to reason with it, using their core values. It&amp;#8217;s not like you have to stop and think about it deeply, you just use what you believe in and apply it on what presents in front of you. While Stoicism is well suited for daily life, in Zen you often need zazen or even monastery isolation to fully accept&amp;nbsp;presence.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="minimalism"&gt;Minimalism&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Minimalism might not be a core practice of Zen philosophy. It&amp;#8217;s more of the result. I, for example, don&amp;#8217;t really enjoy receiving gifts (but especially my parents seems to ignoring this). Yet my library and wardrobe grown considerably in the last few years. But it&amp;#8217;s not &lt;strong&gt;only&lt;/strong&gt; about possessions. Minimalism also applies on habits, workflow, energy management in general. Pareto principle is a great example of minimalism for work and&amp;nbsp;life.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Those are three Zen concepts that I&amp;#8217;m using in daily Stoic life. I&amp;#8217;m on the long path to be a better man (and stoic). Meditation, mindfulness and minimalism are helping me in this journey. If there&amp;#8217;s anything you want to add or just correct me, hit the comments&amp;nbsp;section.&lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Martin Putniorz</dc:creator><pubDate>Tue, 03 Jun 2014 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate><guid>tag:https://sputnikus.github.io,2014-06-03:stoic_zen</guid><category>life</category></item><item><title>Dokku on Debian: Tips &amp; Tricks</title><link>https://sputnikus.github.io/dokku_debian</link><description>&lt;p&gt;As you might know, &lt;a href="https://github.com/progrium/dokku"&gt;Dokku&lt;/a&gt; officially supports Ubuntu (14.04 x64 or 12.04 x64). But Ubuntu (at least on server) is just Debian, so there&amp;#8217;s no reason, why it should not work, right? Wrong - but I&amp;#8217;m gonna show you problems and possible solution, that I&amp;#8217;ve&amp;nbsp;used.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="dokku-installation"&gt;Dokku&amp;nbsp;installation&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First problem you encounter during execution of bootstrap script. It uses &lt;code&gt;add-apt-repository&lt;/code&gt; helper, which is custom Ubuntu command. Workaround is pretty easy, but a little bit messy - you just get your own helper&amp;nbsp;script:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span class="go"&gt;# wget http://blog.anantshri.info/content/uploads/2010/09/add-apt-repository.sh.txt&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="go"&gt;# cp add-apt-repository.sh.txt /usr/sbin/add-apt-repository&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="go"&gt;# chmod o+x /usr/sbin/add-apt-repository&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Now just execute bootstrap again and all should be fine.&amp;nbsp;Right?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="sshcommand"&gt;sshcommand&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dokku is using &lt;a href="https://github.com/progrium/sshcommand"&gt;sshcommand&lt;/a&gt; to propagate itself through &lt;code&gt;ssh&lt;/code&gt;. This is really neat, because during bootstrap &lt;em&gt;dokku&lt;/em&gt; user is created to execute commands remotely. There&amp;#8217;s only a tiny little problem. This user is passwordless and works only on key basis. Which is cool if you are on Ubuntu, because such user is fully operational. Debian on the other hand just &lt;strong&gt;locks it&lt;/strong&gt;. Without password you are screwed even if you disable password auth through &lt;em&gt;secure shell&lt;/em&gt;. Solution? Just add some random password to &lt;em&gt;dokku&lt;/em&gt; user (I&amp;#8217;ve generated it using &lt;a href="http://www.passwordstore.org/"&gt;pass&lt;/a&gt;):&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="kd"&gt;local&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="err"&gt;$&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nb"&gt;pass&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nx"&gt;generate&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nx"&gt;citra&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;/&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nx"&gt;dokku&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="mi"&gt;20&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nx"&gt;remote&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="err"&gt;#&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nx"&gt;usermod&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="na"&gt;-p&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="s1"&gt;&amp;#39;&amp;lt;new_password&amp;gt;&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nx"&gt;dokku&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nx"&gt;remote&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="err"&gt;#&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nx"&gt;passwd&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="na"&gt;-u&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nx"&gt;dokku&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;h2 id="acl-add"&gt;acl-add&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Adding you public key to &lt;em&gt;dokku&lt;/em&gt; control keys is also kinda tricky. Standard command from project &lt;span class="caps"&gt;README&lt;/span&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span class="err"&gt;$&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nx"&gt;cat&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="err"&gt;~&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;/&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nx"&gt;.ssh&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;/&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nx"&gt;id_rsa.pub&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;|&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nx"&gt;ssh&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nx"&gt;progriumapp.com&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="s2"&gt;&amp;quot;sudo sshcommand acl-add dokku &amp;lt;alias&amp;gt;&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;does not work, because (at least in my case), sudo considered parts of my key my passwords (if you are a badass with passwordless sudo, you are going to be fine). So I just executed it on the&amp;nbsp;server:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span class="err"&gt;#&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nx"&gt;sshcommand&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nx"&gt;acl&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="na"&gt;-add&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nx"&gt;dokku&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;&amp;lt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nx"&gt;alias&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nx"&gt;paste&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nb"&gt;key&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)^&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nb"&gt;D&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;h2 id="deploy"&gt;Deploy&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now you should be able to just deploy and use dokku@your_server shell according to &lt;span class="caps"&gt;README&lt;/span&gt;. I&amp;#8217;m considering writing a follow-up about some &lt;a href="https://github.com/progrium/dokku/wiki/Plugins"&gt;plugins&lt;/a&gt; and how to get them working without Ubuntu underneath. Have you encountered any other issues with Dokku on Debian? Please, share it in&amp;nbsp;comments.  &lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Martin Putniorz</dc:creator><pubDate>Thu, 29 May 2014 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate><guid>tag:https://sputnikus.github.io,2014-05-29:dokku_debian</guid><category>devops</category></item><item><title>Jumping into running project</title><link>https://sputnikus.github.io/running_projects</link><description>&lt;p&gt;Recently I&amp;#8217;ve landed a new job in a company with some projects in very advanced state of developement. They gave me time to became familiar with the source code, server layout, operation side of project. I&amp;#8217;ve made a terrible mistake - I was reading the code instead of doing something with&amp;nbsp;it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It&amp;#8217;s almost impossible to learn how to program by only reading the book. It&amp;#8217;s same with the software projects - you have to learn about it by doing it. By tinkering with the codebase, you&amp;#8217;ll get better orientation in it, seeing all the connections between components. By running release on some testing/staging server, you&amp;#8217;ll go through all the steps necessary to deploy&amp;nbsp;application.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That said, it&amp;#8217;s better to start your work on project not by immersing yourself into reading the source code, but by picking up on some issue from GitHub/Trello/etc. and working on it. Very specialized task? Doesn&amp;#8217;t matter, at least you are producing something. Slow progress? Well, still better than reading your eyes off and then spend the same time fixing it. Because you are still mostly paid for editing project, not reading&amp;nbsp;it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So next time you hear somebody telling you: &amp;#8220;We&amp;#8217;re gonna give you time, just go through the source code and then give us some time estimations on tasks X, Y, Z.&amp;#8221;, just answer with: &amp;#8220;I&amp;#8217;m going to work on&amp;nbsp;Z&amp;#8221;.&lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Martin Putniorz</dc:creator><pubDate>Mon, 19 Aug 2013 16:15:00 +0200</pubDate><guid>tag:https://sputnikus.github.io,2013-08-19:running_projects</guid><category>programming</category></item><item><title>Initial Commit</title><link>https://sputnikus.github.io/initial_commit</link><description>&lt;p&gt;What do you say in your first post on new blog? Frankly, I don&amp;#8217;t know. With this I&amp;#8217;m forcing myself a little bit into writing habit. I made couple of short posts, now sitting in my Dropbox, but I want to push this forward, become more&amp;nbsp;consistent.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Don&amp;#8217;t expect me to pull &lt;a href="http://paulgraham.com/" title="Paul Graham's blog"&gt;&lt;span class="caps"&gt;PG&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;-style essays right from the start. Those articles are legendary and if I can make something like that from time to time, I&amp;#8217;ll be&amp;nbsp;happy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Testing gif" src="http://assets.sbnation.com/assets/1349764/Happy_gif.gif" title="Does this even gif?" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;#8217;m interested to write about hacking some stuff (mostly software), my thoughs, geek stuff in general and a lots of other things (see &lt;a href="https://sputnikus.github.io/pages/about"&gt;info&lt;/a&gt; about what I like). I also want to use this opportunity to sharpen my language skills, so feel free to punish my mistakes in comments (also, let&amp;#8217;s see if comments&amp;nbsp;works).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This template will be under heavy development and you can write your opinions about it to &lt;a href="https://sputnikus.github.io/pages/contact-me"&gt;me&lt;/a&gt; or file an &lt;a href="https://github.com/sputnikus/bysputnikus-pelican-theme/issues"&gt;issue&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That&amp;#8217;s it for now, I think. I&amp;#8217;ll be aiming for at least two posts per week (but when there&amp;#8217;s&amp;nbsp;nothing&amp;#8230;).&lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Martin Putniorz</dc:creator><pubDate>Mon, 15 Jul 2013 14:11:00 +0200</pubDate><guid>tag:https://sputnikus.github.io,2013-07-15:initial_commit</guid><category>writing</category><category>misc</category></item></channel></rss>