<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>bysputnikus</title><link>https://sputnikus.github.io/</link><description></description><atom:link href="https://sputnikus.github.io/feeds/main.xml" rel="self"></atom:link><lastBuildDate>Mon, 19 Aug 2013 16:15:00 +0200</lastBuildDate><item><title>Jumping into running project</title><link>https://sputnikus.github.io/running_projects.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;Recently I&amp;#8217;ve landed a new job in a company with some projects in very advanced state of developement. They gave me time to became familiar with the source code, server layout, operation side of project. I&amp;#8217;ve made a terrible mistake - I was reading the code instead of doing something with&amp;nbsp;it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It&amp;#8217;s almost impossible to learn how to program by only reading the book. It&amp;#8217;s same with the software projects - you have to learn about it by doing it. By tinkering with the codebase, you&amp;#8217;ll get better orientation in it, seeing all the connections between components. By running release on some testing/staging server, you&amp;#8217;ll go through all the steps necessary to deploy&amp;nbsp;application.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That said, it&amp;#8217;s better to start your work on project not by immersing yourself into reading the source code, but by picking up on some issue from GitHub/Trello/etc. and working on it. Very specialized task? Doesn&amp;#8217;t matter, at least you are producing something. Slow progress? Well, still better than reading your eyes off and then spend the same time fixing it. Because you are still mostly paid for editing project, not reading&amp;nbsp;it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So next time you hear somebody telling you: &amp;#8220;We&amp;#8217;re gonna give you time, just go through the source code and then give us some time estimations on tasks X, Y, Z.&amp;#8221;, just answer with: &amp;#8220;I&amp;#8217;m going to work on&amp;nbsp;Z&amp;#8221;.&lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Martin Putniorz</dc:creator><pubDate>Mon, 19 Aug 2013 16:15:00 +0200</pubDate><guid>tag:https://sputnikus.github.io,2013-08-19:running_projects.html</guid><category>programming</category></item><item><title>Initial Commit</title><link>https://sputnikus.github.io/initial_commit.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;What do you say in your first post on new blog? Frankly, I don&amp;#8217;t know. With this I&amp;#8217;m forcing myself a little bit into writing habit. I made couple of short posts, now sitting in my Dropbox, but I want to push this forward, become more&amp;nbsp;consistent.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Don&amp;#8217;t expect me to pull &lt;a href="http://paulgraham.com/" title="Paul Graham's blog"&gt;&lt;span class="caps"&gt;PG&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;-style essays right from the start. Those articles are legendary and if I can make something like that from time to time, I&amp;#8217;ll be&amp;nbsp;happy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Testing gif" src="http://assets.sbnation.com/assets/1349764/Happy_gif.gif" title="Does this even gif?" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;#8217;m interested to write about hacking some stuff (mostly software), my thoughs, geek stuff in general and a lots of other things (see &lt;a href="http://sputnikus.github.io/about.html"&gt;info&lt;/a&gt; about what I like). I also want to use this opportunity to sharpen my language skills, so feel free to punish my mistakes in comments (also, let&amp;#8217;s see if comments&amp;nbsp;works).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This template will be under heavy development and you can write your opinions about it to &lt;a href="http://sputnikus.github.io/about.html"&gt;me&lt;/a&gt; or file an &lt;a href="https://github.com/sputnikus/bysputnikus-pelican-theme/issues"&gt;issue&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That&amp;#8217;s it for now, I think. I&amp;#8217;ll be aiming for at least two posts per week (but when there&amp;#8217;s&amp;nbsp;nothing&amp;#8230;).&lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Martin Putniorz</dc:creator><pubDate>Mon, 15 Jul 2013 14:11:00 +0200</pubDate><guid>tag:https://sputnikus.github.io,2013-07-15:initial_commit.html</guid><category>writing</category><category>misc</category></item></channel></rss>